Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary Syllabi and Class Rolls, 1902-1942 MVC0062.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and Junior College Syllabi and Class Rolls
1902-1942
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0062.RG
16 vol. 14 flat boxes
The Mount Vernon Seminary and College began in 1875 as a private high school and junior college for women, founded by Elizabeth J. Somers. The George Washington University initially affiliated with Mount Vernon College, and ultimately acquired the college's property and legacy in 1999. This collection contains bound course syllabi from the Mount Vernon Seminary and Junior College, dating from 1902 to 1942. Each syllabus includes a list of enrolled students.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains bound course syllabi from the Mount Vernon Seminary and Junior College, dating from 1902 to 1942. Each syllabus includes a list of enrolled students. The syllabi cover courses such as English Literature, French, Spanish, Latin, Bible History, Ancient History, Medieval History, Modern History, Civics and American History, Art History, History of Architecture, Interior Decoration, Studio Art, Business Arithmetic, Bookeeping, Algebra, Geometry, Physiology, Chemistry, Astronomy, Botany, Psychology, Sociology, Parliamentary Law, Domestic Science, Sewing, Shorthand, Typewriting, Costume Design, Drama, Speech, and Music.
Biographical / Historical
The Mount Vernon Seminary was officially established by Elizabeth Somers in 1875; she named it after her brother's church in Baltimore, Mount Vernon Place Methodist. The Seminary began as a six year prepatory school, with four years of high school level classes, and two years of post-high school curriculum, calling it a "Family and Day School for Young Ladies." In order to graduate, students had to complete a formal process of "Senior Essays" in which they completed primary research and wrote on a current political or social topic, including such provocative issues as child labor, prohibition, poverty, and women's suffrage. In the 1920 graduating class, eight women continued their education at universities such as the University of Wisconsin, Stanford, Northwestern and the University of Texas; by 1923 graduates were going to such other prestigious universities as UC-Berkeley, Columbia, Cornell, Smith College and the University of Chicago. Such advancements in higher education were uncommon for women of the day, but Mount Vernon was one of the premier prepatory institutions in the country.
In 1927, Mount Vernon established a Junior College, and with its establishment, students no longer had to complete six years of courses to receive a diploma; they graduated from the Seminary after four years and could continue on to the Junior College for two more years of college preparation. After World War II began, the U.S. Navy took over the campus as a part of the war effort; in 1945 the school purchased 21 acres on Foxhall Road and surrounding areas, and had applied for accreditation to award Associates of Arts Degrees after completing two years of the Junior College.
Despite its expansion, by 1965 the Board of Trustees voted unanimously to dissolve the Seminary by 1969, as it could not financially support both institutions. During the 1960s, the Junior College developed new academic concentrations such as government, international relations and political science to reflect its location in the nation's capital. At the same time, it began to phase out its vocational training such as home economics and secretarial skills to make room for these higher education courses.
By 1973, the Board of Higher Education licensed the college to award Bachelor of Arts (BA) degrees such as Public Affairs, Government, Business Administration, Childhood, Special Education, and the Visual Arts, as well as honorary Doctor of Humane Letters and Juris Doctor Degrees; in 1976, the college received initial accreditation as a four-year college and was reaccredited ten years later. However, by 1996 the college announced a plan to affiliate with George Washington University; in 1999 the last class of Mount Vernon College graduated. Today, as an affiliated campus of GWU, Mount Vernon offers special living accommodations, as well as learning and leadership programs for female students.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Mount Vernon Seminary and College archives were acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. The collection was transferred to the Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Bib#
8862410
Women's colleges; Education -- Curricula; Women -- Education; Mount Vernon Seminary
- Syllabi and Class Rolls Volume 1, 1902-1905; Series 1 (Flat box 1, Volume 1)
- Syllabi and Class Rolls Volume 2, 1905-1908; Series 1 (Flat box 2, Volume 2)
- Syllabi and Class Rolls Volumes 3-5, 1911-1917; Series 1 (Flat box 3, Volume 5, Volume 4, Volume 3)
- Syllabi and Class Rolls Volume 6, 1917-1919; Series 1 (Flat box 4, Volume 6)
- Syllabi and Class Rolls Volume 7, 1919-1921; Series 1 (Flat box 5, Volume 7)
- Syllabi and Class Rolls Volume 8, 1921-1923; Series 1 (Flat box 6, Volume 8)
- Syllabi and Class Rolls Volume 9, 1923-1925; Series 1 (Flat box 7, Volume 9)
- Syllabi and Class Rolls Volume 10, 1925-1927; Series 1 (Flat box 8, Volume 10)
- Syllabi and Class Rolls Volume 11, 1927-1929; Series 1 (Flat box 9, Volume 11)
- Syllabi and Class Rolls Volume 12, 1929-1932; Series 1 (Flat box 10, Volume 12)
- Syllabi and Class Rolls Volume 13, 1932-1936; Series 1 (Flat box 11, Volume 13)
- Syllabi and Class Rolls Volume 14, 1936-1939; Series 1 (Flat box 12, Volume 14)
- Syllabi and Class Rolls Volume 15, 1939-1940; Series 1 (Flat box 13, Volume 15)
- Syllabi and Class Rolls Volume 16, 1939-1940; Series 1 (Flat box 14, Volume 16)